Guide to the James Laughlin Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
James Laughlin papers
1939-1994
1976-1994
YCAL MSS 654
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.64
(5 boxes)
The James Laughlin Papers contain writings by Laughlin and others, an award acceptance speech by Laughlin, papers and audiocassettes relating to "New Directions at 50," the 50th Anniversary of New Directions exhibition at the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University, and various material removed from printed volumes.
Laughlin, James, 1914-1997
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of James Laughlin, 1986-2005.
1988-2005, printed volumes were accessioned in Printed Acquisitions. 2008, material was accessioned in Manuscript Unit.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 5 (audiocassettes): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Associated Materials
Printed material received with the collection was removed for separate cataloging and can be accessed by searching Orbis (Yale's Online Catalog).
James Laughlin (1914-1997)
James Laughlin, American poet and literary book publisher who founded New Directions Publishing.
Scope and Contents
The James Laughlin Papers contain writings by Laughlin and others, an award acceptance speech by Laughlin, papers and audiocassettes relating to "New Directions at 50," the 50th Anniversary of New Directions exhibition at the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University, and various material removed from printed volumes.
Arrangement
Organized into four groupings: I. June 1986 Acquisition, 1986 June. II. June 1986 Acquisition, 1986. III. May 1989 Acquisition, 1976-1989. IV.1988-2005 Acquisitions, 1949-1996.
Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Editors -- United States; Poets, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Publishers and publishing -- United States; Publishers and publishing -- United States -- Exhibitions; Audiovisual materials; Sound recordings; Authors -- 20th Century; Editors -- 20th Century; Poets -- 20th Century; Laughlin, James, 1914-1997; Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library; New Directions Publishing Corp
- June 1986 Acquisition, 1986 June; 1; 0.22; (2 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Formerly Uncat ZA MS 489
  - "New Directions at 50." 50th Anniversary of New Directions exhibition at the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University, prepared by John Harrison
    - Photograph of Laughlin and unidentified individuals; and corresponding contact sheet for photographs of Laughlin with various unidentified individuals, 1986 June (Box 1)
    - Yale Weekly Bulletin and Calendar, printed version, 1986 June 9-16 (Box 1)
    - Lecture by James Laughlin, welcome by David Schoonover, introduction by Penelope Lawrens (1 of 2), 1986 June 12; 1; 00:47:29; Static and a high amount of hiss can be heard on the tape. (Box 5, Item barcode 39002109972167)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Use of originals is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    - Lecture by James Laughlin, welcome by David Schoonover, introduction by Penelope Lawrens (2 of 2), 1986 June 12; 1; 00:10:05; Static and a high amount of hiss can be heard on the tape. (Box 5, Item barcode 39002109972175)
- June 1986 Acquisition, 1986, undated; 2
  Formerly Uncat ZA File 152
  - Connecticut Commission on the Arts award acceptance speech, typescript photocopy; and "Some Voices from Canto 74" typescript photocopy, 1986 May 31, undated (Box 1)
- May 1989 Acquisition, 1976-1989, undated; 3; 2; (2 boxes)
  Formerly Uncat ZA MS 106
  Contains various drafts of writings by Laughlin and others, including typescripts, original and photocopy, galley proofs, and notes.
  - American Theatre Society memo, 1977 April (Box 2)
  - Washington Summer theater correspondence, ads, clippings, and other papers, 1976 (Box 2)
  - Carpenter, Humphrey. A Serious Character: The Life of Ezra Pound, typescript draft, photocopy, circa 1988; 10 (Box 2)
    Includes note, "First draft of Carpenter's biography of Pound sent to Laughlin for vetting. Craig Raine, editor at Faber and Faber, made him rewrite a lot of it, which it needed."
  - Laughlin, James. The Bird of Endless Time: Poems by James Laughlin, galleys, photocopy, undated (Box 2)
  - Laughlin, James. Pound as Wuz: Essays and Lectures on Ezra Pound
    - Galleys, photocopy, circa 1987; 2 (Box 2)
    - Various typescript drafts, notes and photocopy galleys, circa 1987; 10 (Box 2)
    - Various typescript drafts, notes and photocopy galleys, circa 1987; 20 (Box 3)
  - Levertov, Denise. Door in the Hive, typescript draft, photocopy, undated (Box 3)
  - Stough, Christina C. "The Literary Relationship of T. S. Eliot and Ezra Pound after 'The Waste Land'", 1980 June (Box 3)
  - Williams, William Carlos. "Detail and Parody for the Poem 'Paterson'," typescript draft, photocopy (Box 3)
    Preliminary verse sketches. Photocopy of presentation copy inscribed to James Laughlin, 1939 March 9.
  - Witemeyer, Hugh. William Carlos Williams and James Laughlin: Selected Letters, typescript draft, corrected, 1989; 2 (Box 3)
- 1988-2005 Acquisitions, 1949-1994; 4; 0.42; (1 box)
  Formerly Uncat MSS 1017. Accessioned by Manuscript Unit in 2008.
  - Material removed from printed volumes in various accessions and transferred from Printed Acquisitions to Manuscript Unit., 1949-1994; 27 (Box 4)
    Includes writings by Denise Levertov, Kenneth Rexroth, Gustaf Sobin, and Tennessee Williams